# François Leblanc

### Senior Data Engineer at Shopify

### leblancfg@gmail.com

Gatineau, Québec, Canada 819.208.4089

leblancfg.com

### Top Skills

- Software Engineering
- Data Science
- Machine Learning

### Languages

- French (Native)
- English (Native equivalent)

### Summary

Experienced data professional with a demonstrated history of problem solving. Skilled in Python and its data and science stacks, Unix, GIS, Computer Vision, Machine Learning and Software Development. Strong engineering skills in data pipelines, data warehousing, application backend, and cloud computing.

Likes to go wide and have a broad skillset. Excited both by working on new problem domains or going deep on existing ones.

### Experience

### Shopify

#### Senior Data Engineer - People Analytics

May 2020 - Present Gatineau, Québec, Canada

• Building a data warehouse for People Analytics, using Airflow, BigQuery (formerly PostgreSQL), dbt, and Looker

- Building and maintaining versioned statistical and machine learning models for People Analytics, using Python
- Building the "OS" of Shopify's HR with data pipelines that structure the main building blocks for HR across the company: disciplines, compensation, performance, etc.
- Built a company-wise static website for Shopify's "OS" of HR, using Remix (React) and MDX
- Built an internal Slack survey tool for People Analytics, using FastAPI and PostgreSQL.
- Built an internal survey self-service tool for managers, using Looker.

#### Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat

#### **Data Scientist**

April 2019 - May 2020 Ottawa, Canada

- Building a Data Science environment for secure data on Azure cloud, used by other Data Science teams across the department (60+ users)
- Prototyping Machine Learning / Statistics applications with teams of ana lysts across the department: Data Engineering, NLP, regression modeling
- Led a 10-week interdepartmental Bayesian Inference study group, in collaboration with the Canadian School of Public Service's Digital Academy

### **Environment and Climate Change Canada**

#### **Data Scientist**

August 2018 - April 2019 Gatineau, Québec

Working in ECCC's Data Lab, in a multi-disciplinary team tasked with developing data solutions to key problems throughout the department. Rapid development of data solutions by use of statistics, machine learning, data engineering, and visualization (Python, SQL, PowerBI, Tableau)

- Used deep learning to automate bird counting and positioning from aerial imagery (Python, Keras, Azure)
- Used text analytics techniques for public consultations (Python, gensim, spacy) streamlining the analysis process of program analysts to effectively understand what is being said through thousands of comments
- Automating the rider sign-in for the departmental shuttles, using onboard tablets equipped with employee card readers (PHP, PowerBI, Azure)

#### Physical Science Officer

October 2017 - August 2018 Gatineau, Québec Tracking Pollution in Canada for the National Pollutant Release Inventory (NPRI). Ensuring the data on pollutant release is up to date and relevant to the needs of its users: internal to ECCC, environmental researchers, environmental NGOs and the Canadian public.

- Dealing with everything geospatial-related: publishing map layers on Open Data portal, spatial statistics, Quality Assurance of self-reported data (Python, PostGIS, Leaflet.js, Esri ArcMap and ArcGIS Online)
- Communicating pollution science to the Candian public: led a series of interactive sector overviews on Canadian industrial sectors (ArcGIS Online), the creation of NPRI infographics, and a NPRI "smelling booth" at the Eureka science festival in Montréal.

### Data and Visualization Analyst

December 2015 - October 2017 Gatineau, Québec

Helping ECCC's HR Branch to easily extract, interact with, compare and visualize their HR data.

- Set up data pipelines to automate the extraction, transformation and loading (ETL) of data from its various databases into explorable datasets
- Led the development and maintenance of a dozen bilingual Tableau dash boards for use by HR Advisors, managers and senior executives for the analysis and planning of Human Resource needs across the department.

#### Canadian Space Agency

#### Mission Planner - Data Acquisition

March 2017 - August 2017 St-Hubert, Québec

- Provided Synthetic Aperture Radar (SAR) satellite imagery to Government of Canada clients, university research teams and the "Space & Major Disasters" International Charter
- Oversaw and co-wrote a fully-tested and documented Python package to automate RADARSAT-2 image acquisition plan tasks
- Planned the acquisition programs of RADARSAT-2 imagery for research, national security and humanitarian aid operations

#### Transport Canada

#### **Production Support Specialist**

June 2015 - November 2015 Ottawa, Ontario

- Automated government ID card production (Python, OpenCV, bash)
- Audited and analyzed the workflow for the Inspector Equipment warehouse

• Helped streamline the financial coding for postal services (Excel, VBA).

# Où Quoi? Salon Urbain

# Bartender, Menu Director

April 2012 - June 2015 Gatineau, Québec

# Education

# UC Irvine, Extension

2015 - 2019

Data Science Certificate, Sciences and Information Technologies

### University of Ottawa

2007 - 2012

Bachelor of Science (B.Sc.), Geology, Physics